I love English learners.
Welcome back to another
great lesson here at English
Pod. My name is Marco.
And I'm Erica. And today
we are going to have
a lesson that is going
to be very useful when
you arrive late. Yes,
well we all have arrived
late to something and
we need a good way of
saying sorry and
saying why we were late.
So today we're not only going
to be looking at vocabulary
used to explain why
you are late but also some
typical excuses of
why people are late.
Right, so some normal reasons
for saying why you're late.
Well why don't we get
started with the dialogue.
Now we're going to hear
five people in the dialogue.
So at the beginning
we'll hear the boss
and the assistant and then we'll
hear three people who are arriving late.
Where is everyone? We were
supposed to start 15 minutes ago.
Joe called and said
she'd be here in a sec.
She said she got
tied up with a client.
Sorry I'm late everyone.
Oh there was a huge
traffic jam on the
highway this morning.
Morning everyone. Are you
stuck in traffic as well, Jess?
There was a huge pile
up on the highway and
traffic was backed up
for miles. Scott just called
and said that he's running late. His last
meeting ran over but he's on his way now.
Guys, this is not acceptable.
If I say the meeting starts at
10, the meeting starts at 10.
Not 10.01 and
definitely not 10.20.
All right, let's get started.
So the first thing I want to talk
about is our-I'm sorry
everyone. I know I'm late
but really it's not my
fault. I was getting a
coffee at Starbucks and the
line was way way too long.
I was waiting for 20
minutes to get my coffee.
All right, so well good excuses
in general except the last one.
I don't think that's such a good excuse
of why you're late, right? Yeah, I don't
really think if I was
the boss I would be very
happy with this employee.
Yeah, I don't think
coffee is that important.
But some of the excuses
were good and some of
the language they used to
describe the excuses
was really great.
So let's look at that now
in language takeaway.
Language takeaway. All right,
on language takeaway today we
have four words that
we're going to be looking
at and well let's get
started with the first one.
So Jo called the office
assistant and explained
that she will be late
because she got tied up
with a client to get tied up.
So I got tied up with a client.
All right, this is a really common reason
for being late but why don't we listen to
some examples to help us
understand what it means.
Example one.
Sorry I'm late honey.
I got tied up at the office.
Example two.
I was tied up on the phone all
afternoon and didn't get any work done.
Example three.
I got tied up in traffic on the way here.
All right, so if you get
tied up it means that
you get busy with something
that you can't avoid.
Right, you're busy with
something that's so important.
It's like you are tied
by a rope to that thing.
Okay, I got tied up.
I'm sorry, I got tied
up. Yep. All right, now
the first person that
arrived to the office will explain that
there was a huge traffic jam on the highway.
A traffic jam.
A huge traffic jam.
Now we understand traffic, right?
Cars, a lot of cars.
Yeah, so a jam, it means that it
was like blocked. It was stopped.
It was stopped.
Yeah.
There were a lot of cars on the
highway and they weren't moving.
So a huge traffic jam is a
very, very big stopping of cars.
Now our next word explains why
sometimes there is a traffic jam.
Watch.
Well, we found out that
there was a huge pileup.
A pileup.
A huge pileup.
Okay, a huge pileup. Now if a pileup is
another way of saying an accident, right?
Yeah, an accident with many cars and
they all get piled on top of each other.
All right, so many cars
got into an accident.
Yeah, so this could be a reason
of why there was a traffic jam.
And also a reason for why you were late.
All right.
Now the other person Scott also
called and he said that he's running late.
He's running late.
I'm running late.
Now if I'm running late,
it might actually running
somewhere, what am I
doing? What's happening?
You are going to be late and
you know you're going to be late.
Okay, I know I'm going to be late.
So I'll call you and I'll say,
hey, I'm running a little bit late.
Yeah, actually, this is the most common
thing I say when I'm going to be late.
And I think it's really important
to know how to use this phrase.
So let's hear some more examples.
Example one.
Jane is running late.
She'll be here in 10 minutes.
Example two.
Traffic is really bad.
So I'm running late.
Example three.
I'm running a bit late.
So please start without me.
All right, perfect.
So running late, a very common way of
explaining that you're going to be late.
And well, it makes you sound very native.
Yeah, it's a great phrase.
Now our last phrase, what
we heard, the reason why Scott
was running late was because
his last meeting ran over.
Okay, to run over my meeting ran over.
Now, ran over my meeting ran over.
It means it went too far.
Well, when something
runs over, it goes longer.
Okay, longer than expected.
Yeah, so a meeting can run over
or an appointment can run over.
So I can say my meeting
ran over 15 minutes.
I'm going to be a little bit late.
That's right.
A great excuse.
Very good.
Five great words.
And well, I think it's time for us to
listen to this dialogue and understand these
words as they were used
in the dialogue, and then
we'll come back and take
a look at more phrases.
Where is everyone?
We were supposed to start 15 minutes ago.
Joe called and said she'd be here in a sec.
She said she got tied up with a client.
Sorry, I'm late, everyone.
There was a huge traffic jam
on the highway this morning.
Morning, everyone.
Were you stuck in traffic as well, Jess?
There was a huge pileup on the highway,
and traffic was backed up for miles.
Scott just called and
said that he's running late.
His last meeting ran over,
but he's on his way now.
Guys, this is not acceptable.
If I say the meeting starts at 10,
the meeting starts at 10, not 1001,
and definitely not 1020.
All right, let's get started.
So the first thing I want to talk
about is our... I'm really sorry, everyone.
I know I'm late, but
really, it's not my fault.
I was getting a coffee at Starbucks,
and the line was way too long.
I was waiting for 20
minutes to get my coffee.
Okay, we got some some more
great praises for describing being late.
Let's look at them now.
Influency builder.
Fluency builder.
When Joe called, she
said she'd be there in a sec.
I'll be here in a sec.
So when someone will be here in a
sec, it means they'll be here very soon.
Okay.
I'll be here in a sec.
I'll be there in a sec.
But what about this word, sec?
It's a short way of saying second.
So SEC.
A sec.
Now, it's an exaggeration, obviously,
because you won't be there in one second,
but you're just explaining that
you'll be there very, very soon.
What about the
difference between I'll be
here in a sec, and I'll
be here in a minute?
Well, if you say I'll be there in a sec, it
means I'll be there in one minute, right?
But if you say, oh, I'll
be there in a minute.
It could be a minute or more
like three or four or five minutes.
Yeah, I think that's true.
Now again, going
back to this traffic issue,
we saw that somebody was
stuck in traffic to be stuck in traffic.
I got stuck in traffic.
Now, when you're stuck
in traffic, you can't drive
because there are too many
cars stopped on the highway.
So you are actually in the traffic.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're stopped
there for like 20 minutes.
You can't move.
Okay, I'm stuck in traffic.
I'm going to be late.
Mm-hmm, really great excuse.
And the reason they
were stuck in traffic
was because traffic
was backed up for miles.
Okay, traffic is backed up for miles.
To be backed up for miles.
Now, if I say the traffic
is backed up for miles,
it means that it's very
long or how does that work?
Well, okay, imagine there is an
accident and that has caused a traffic jam.
And the cars are lined up
for for many miles behind you.
Okay, so it's backed up from that point.
There are many miles
of cars waiting to pass.
Yep.
So it's backed up for miles.
Very good.
So great phrases.
And I think it's
appropriate for us to listen
to the dialogue for
the very last time.
And then we'll come back and talk a little
bit more about this being on time issue.
Where is everyone?
We were supposed to start 15 minutes ago.
Joe Colton said she'd be here in a sec.
She said she got tied up with a client.
Sorry, I'm late, everyone.
Oh, there was a huge traffic
jam on the highway this morning.
Morning, everyone.
Are you stuck in traffic as well, Jess?
There was a huge pile up on the highway.
And traffic was backed up for miles.
Scott just called and
said that he's running late.
His last meeting ran over,
but he's on his way now.
Guys, this is not acceptable.
If I say the meeting
starts at 10, the meeting
starts at 10, not 10, 0, 1,
and definitely not 10, 20.
All right.
Let's get started.
So the first thing I want to talk
about is our-- I'm sorry, everyone.
I know I'm late, but
really, it's not my fault.
I was getting a coffee at Starbucks
and the line was way, way too long.
I was waiting for 20
minutes to get my coffee.
Well, Marco, I know that
ideas about time and ideas
about being late are
different in different countries.
Yeah.
In different countries, people treat
time or being on time in different ways.
Yeah.
Like, I'm from Canada,
and I look at being
on time really different
than you do, right?
Yes, because for example, if
you call for a meeting at 9 o'clock,
yeah, usually people will be there at 9
o'clock because the meeting will start.
In America.
Right, in America.
Now, for example, Latin
America, we do have this.
What we call sometimes the Latino time
or Hispanic time, which is like 9 o'clock
is like the time that everyone should
be there, but until people get there,
get their coffee, and whatever,
then it'll be 9/15, maybe up to 9/30.
And I think it's a
little bit even more
noticeable when we're
talking about social events.
Like, if you go to someone's house
for dinner in Canada, if they say,
come to my house at 6 o'clock for dinner,
you'll be there at 6 o'clock, right?
Okay, yeah, yeah, usually you'll be there
only a couple of minutes after the time
that was specified just to, you know,
give the house owner a little bit of time.
Yep.
But if we have a dinner invitation for 6,
we know that it's not really going to begin
eating at 6 o'clock, people
will get there at 6/30 or 7.
And of course food isn't
ready until like maybe 8 or 9.
But in German countries,
from what I know,
you've got to be, if they say be there at
6, they're at 6,000, right, not 6 o'clock.
And also, I think it's about
when people start work, right?
Yeah.
On time, you have to begin work.
Sometimes it's
acceptable to be 10 or 15
minutes so-called late, but
in other places, you know?
Yeah, North America,
if you're supposed to
start work at 9, you have to
be at your desk working at 9.
At 9.
Yeah, see that in
other countries, people
get there at 9, get their coffee, maybe
take a quick glance at their emails or the
newspaper and then, you know,
start working at around 9/30 or 10.
So I guess the important
thing is to know
what the tradition is in
the country where you are.
Exactly.
So come to our website, EnglishPod.com, and
let us know how it works in your countries.
I know that many
different countries have a
different way of treating
time, so share it with us.
Yes.
And remember, if you have any questions,
please ask them at the website as well.
We're out of time today, but
until next time, thanks for listening.
And goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]